<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christs order, and the disciples practice concerning the ministers maintenance, and releeving of the poore: whereby the claiming tithes, or any thing in stead thereof, appeares to be contrary to the Gospel.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79548</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3968</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E54_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209920</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868766</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868766</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121122</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79548)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121122)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 10:E54[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christs order, and the disciples practice concerning the ministers maintenance, and releeving of the poore: whereby the claiming tithes, or any thing in stead thereof, appeares to be contrary to the Gospel.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tithes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121122:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>CHRISTS ORDER, AND THE Diſciples practice concerning the Miniſters maintenance, and releeving of the Poore: whereby the claiming Tithes, or any thing in ſtead thereof, appeares to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Goſpel.</head>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>MAtth. 10.10.</bibl> The workman is worthy of his meat.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Luke 10.5.7.</bibl> Into whatſoever houſe ye enter, remaine eating and drinking ſuch things as they give, for the labourer is worthy of his hire.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Gal. 6.6.</bibl> Let him that is taught in the Word, communicate unto him that teacheth, in all good things.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>1 Cor. 9.7.14.</bibl> Who goeth to warfare any time at his owne charges? who planteth a Vineyard, and eateth not of the fruit thereof? or who feedeth a flocke, and eateth not of the milke of the flocke? Even ſo hath the Lord or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, that they which preach the Goſpel, ſhould live by the Goſpel.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Act. 6.2, 3, 4.</bibl> Then the twelve called the multitude of the Diſciples unto them, and ſaid, It is not reaſon that wee ſhould leave the word of God, and ſerve Tables: wherefore Brethren looke ye out among you ſeven men of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt report, full of the holy Ghoſt and wiſedome, whom wee may appoint over this buſineſſe, but we will give our ſelves continually to prayer, and to the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrie of the word.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>C. 2.44, 45.</bibl> All that beleeved were together and had all things common, and ſold their poſſeſsions and goods and parted them to all men, as every man had need.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>C. 4.32.</bibl> Neither ſaid any of them that ought of the things which he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed was his owne but they had all things in common.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Rom. 15.26, 27.</bibl> It hath pleaſed them of Macedonia and Achaia to make a certaine contribution for the poore which were at Ieruſalem: It hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them verily and their d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ars they are: For if the Gentiles have beene made partakers of their ſpirituall things, their duty is alſo to adminiſter unto them in carnall things.</p>
            </q>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:121122:2"/>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>2 Cor. 8.3, 4.</bibl> To their power (I beare record) yea and beyond their power they were willing of themſelves, praying us with much entreaty, that wee would receive the gift, and take upon us the fellowſhip of adminiſtring to the Saints.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>C. 9.5.</bibl> I thought it neceſſary to exh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt the brethren that they would goe before unto you, and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke up beforehand the bounty, whereof ye had notice before, that the ſame might be ready as a matter of bounty, and not of cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe; every man according as he purpoſes in his heart, ſo let him give, not grudgingly.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>1 Cor. 9.11, 12, 13, 14.</bibl> If we have ſowne unto you ſpirituall things, is it a great thing it we ſhould reape your carnall things? If others be partakers of this power over you, are not we rather? Nevertheleſſe we have not uſed this power, but ſuffer all things, leſt we ſhould hinder the Goſpel of Chriſt. Doe ye not know that they which miniſter about holy things, live of the things of the Temple? and they which watt at the Altar are partakers of the Altar? even ſo hath the Lord ordained that they which preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>V. 15, 18, 23.</bibl> But I have uſed none of theſe things, neither have I writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hings that it ſhould be ſo done unto me, for it were better for me to dye, than that any man ſhould make my glorying void. What is my reward then? verily that where I preach the Goſpel, I may make the Goſpel of Chriſt without charge, that I abuſe not my power in the Goſpel. And this I doe for the Goſpel ſake, that I might be partaker thereof with you.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>C. 4 14.</bibl> I write not theſe things to ſhame you, but as my beloved ſonnes to warne you.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>2 Cor. 4.5.</bibl> We preach our ſelves your ſervants for Ieſus ſake.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>1 Cor. 4.11, 12.</bibl> Even unto this preſent houre we both hunger and thirſt, and are naked and buffeted and have no certaine dwelling place, and labour, working with our owne hands.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Acts 18.3.</bibl> And becauſe Paul was of the ſame craft, he abode with Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la and Priſcilla, and wrought for by their occupation they were Tent makers.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>C. 20.33 34, 35.</bibl> I have coveted no mans ſilver, or gold or apparell yea you your ſerves know that theſe hands have miniſtred unto my neceſsities, and to them that were with me: I have ſhewed you all things, how that ſo la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121122:2"/>ye ought to ſupport the weake, and to remember the words of the Lord Ieſus, how he ſaid, it is more bleſſed to give than to receive.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>2 Cor. 11.7, 8, 9, 10.</bibl> Have I committed an offence in chaſing my ſelfe that you might be exalted? becauſe I have preached to you the Goſpel of God freely? I have robbed other Churches to doe you ſervice. When I was preſent with you and wanted, I was chargeable to no man, for that which was lacking to me, the brethren which came from Macedonia ſupplyed, and in all things I have kept my ſelfe from being burthenſome unto you, and ſo will I keepe my ſelfe, as the truth of Chriſt is in me, no man ſhall ſtop me of this boaſting in the Regions of Achaia.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Act. 3.6.</bibl> Peter ſaid ſilver &amp; gold have I none, but ſuch as I have give I thee.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>2 Cor. 12.13, 14</bibl> What is it wherein ye were inferiour to other Churches, except it be that I my ſelfe was not burthenſome unto you? forgive mee this wrong: behold the third time I am ready to come unto you, and I will not be burthenſome unto you, for I ſeeke not yours but you, for the children ought not to lay up for the parents, but the parents for the children.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>V. 16, 17, 18.</bibl> I did not burthen you, nevertheleſſe being crafty I caught you with guile. Did I make againe of you by any of them which I ſent unto you? I deſired Titus, and with him I ſent a brother: did Titus make a gaine of you? walked we not in the ſame ſpirit? walked we not in the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me ſteps?</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Phil. 4.15.16, 17.</bibl> Now ye Philippians know alſo that in the beginning of the Goſpel when I departed from Macedonia, no Church communicated with me as concerning giving and receiving but ye onely, for even in Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonica ye ſent once and gaine to my neceſsity, not becauſe I deſire a gift, but I deſire fruit, that we may abound to your account.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>1 Theſſ. 2.9.</bibl> Ye may remember our labouring night and day, becauſe we would not be chargeable unto any of you.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>C. 4.11, 12.</bibl> Doe your owne buſineſſe, worke with your owne hands (as we commanded you) that ye may walke honeſtly towards them that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and that yee may have lacke of nothing.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>2 Theſſ. 3.8.10.</bibl> We did not eat any mans bread for nought, but wrought with labour and travaile night and day that wee might not bee chargeable to any of you; for even when we were with you this we commanded you, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> any would not worke he ſhould not eate.</p>
            </q>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:121122:3"/>
            <p>THe beſt Chriſtians of the Primitive times had <hi>all things in common,</hi> and without all diſpute and controverſie, wee ought to hold nothing ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and peculiar unto us, but that wee ſhould ſee our ſelves obliged to part with it, not onely for Gods more immediate worſhip and ſervice, but alſo for ſuſtenance, reliefe and comfort of the meaneſt brother upon the face of the earth. We are but Stewards of what wee have, and are all one day to give account thereof to the Great Maſter of the Houſhold, and of <hi>ſuch as have had moſt, of them ſhall be required moſt, Luke</hi> 12 48. Who thinke we then muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for ſo many as have fallen into ſickneſſes, and at laſt died in our very ſtreets and priſons of penury and want, whilſt we have ſurfetted with abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance? But to <hi>ſuch as labour in the Miniſtrie,</hi> to ſuch as diſpence unto us of the heavenly Manna, towards theſe we have a ſtronger tye, not onely that their neceſſities may be releeved, but that thereby they may be more free from worldly care and temptations, enabled to be <hi>hoſpitable and bountifull unto others that ſtand in want,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.8. There is an obligation hereof in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of God, but it was voluntary and ought not to be compulſive in reſpect of man: And therefore <hi>Paul,</hi> whether in regard hee feared his Diſciples would not relliſh the Goſpel ſo pleaſantly, if in any manner it became charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, or becauſe hee ſaw that contributions towards his maintenance would come heavily from them, or for what other reſpect ſoever, rather than hee would put it to the hazard, hee doth not onely forbeare to preſſe for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward which was due unto his Miniſtery, but yeelds divers exceeding preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant reaſons, why others ought and are obliged to doe the like, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.35. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14. and 12.14. And as of two evils we are to chooſe the leaſt, ſo of two good things we are bound to doe the beſt: we muſt rather preach the Goſpel gratis, than inſiſt ſo much upon our maintenance, that it become diſtaſtfull.</p>
            <p>But of farre different temper are ſuch, who yearly, quarterly, or the like, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of the people certain ſet ſums of mony, or Tithes, as the hackney wages of their miniſtery, forcing them that have reſiſted in ſuch violent manner, as the whole Pariſh, though at firſt they approved their doctrine, became at laſt aweary and in hatred of their perſons: 'Tis true, they had preſcription, and certaine Civill Lawes to juſtifie their proceedings, but were they not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted at firſt by Poperie, the myſtery of iniquity, and by them for their owne ends conveyed unto us? Let us examine how they agree with the Goſpel of J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s Chriſt, who againſt ſuch times prepared and ſent forth his Apoſtles, and in them all Miniſters ſucceſſively, with a <hi>freely yee have received, freely give; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Mat.</hi> 10 8. Or have they any reſemblance with the ſpirit of <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> beene better for him to dye, than that hee ſhould want the glory of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121122:3"/>not making the Goſpell chargeable to the Corinthians, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.15.18. Oh how ought they to tremble who have gone point blanck againſt the evidence of ſuch a truth? Beſides, may we not juſtly feare theſe Popiſh badges, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining ſtill in Gods juſt judgement, may prove a ſoveraigne bait and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to intice thoſe ſlow bellies to us againe, who firſt eſtabliſhed them? But is it not moſt evident, that throughout the whole Goſpel there is not one word found to countenance a forcing of the people to contribute unto the poore, or to the miniſtry any thing, but what they pleaſe themſelves? if tithes or ſuch like maintenance were due now under the Goſpel by virtue of the Moſaicall Law, doubtleſſe our Saviour and his Apoſtles would have ſignified ſo much. 'Tis true, that certaine paſſages of theirs are miſtaken by ſome, as if they ſeemed to glance thereat, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.18. but that was only ſo farre forth as wee are ſtill bound by the equity thereof in <hi>foro conſcientia,</hi> not to the literall obſervance <hi>in foro fori,</hi> as no wayes ſuiting with thoſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall expreſſions of <hi>Pauls,</hi> in urging it onely as voluntary in thoſe which were to give it, and his owne practice in not requiring it as a legall duty: for his owne behoofe, and inſtructing others to doe the ſame, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.17, 18. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if it were legally due, why did not <hi>Paul</hi> compell them to the payment of it? Did he want meanes or power ſo to doe? Surely ſuch as have the gift of miracles cannot be ſaid to want helpe to right themſelves, and vindicate Gods portion? and we may ſee <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>in the beginning,</hi> that <hi>Peter</hi> knew full well his owne ſtrength, and made uſe of it in ſuch a caſe; when <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> having put themſelves into the number of the Diſciples, to ſhow they did, at leaſt, deſire to ſeeme like the reſt, ſold a poſſeſſion, and made as if they had laid the whole value thereof at the Apoſtles feet, but ſecretly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held part thereof; for which groſſe hypocriſie, <hi>Peter</hi> puniſhed them no leſſe miraculouſly than ſeverely with death, ſaying, <hi>Whilſt it remained was it not thine owne? and after it was ſold, was it not in thine owne power? why haſt thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this thing in thine heart? thou haſt not lyed unto men, but unto the holy Ghoſt, Act.</hi> 5.4. From whence we may gather a cleare argument, that they were not forced to any allowance of Tythes, or ought elſe in ſtead thereof: for had there been any ſuch like duty due to God in his Miniſters according to the Letter, (I ſay not according to the equity thereof) it was as much due be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the poſſeſſion was ſold, before it was laid downe at the Apoſtles feet devoted to the ſervice of the Saints, as it was afterwards; the civill proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters conſent gaines neither unto God nor to his Saints under the Goſpel ever a whit the better title to any earthly goods in reſpect of the right or thing it ſelfe; but in reſpect to the manner of receiving it in a legall compulſive civill way, if the intereſſed having once given conſent, may afterwards continue
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121122:4"/>(but refuſe) paiment of it without defilement to their conſciences. <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> were not ſtruck dead for denying almes unto the poore Saints, or maintenance unto the miniſtry; but becauſe they played the hypocrites ſo groſſely, ſeeking to bee thought more liberall than their covetous deſires would give them leave: And yet we may not thinke that denying almes and maintenance were a leſſer ſin than hypocriſie; or that hypocrites may now be puniſhed with death by Civill Magiſtrates: but as in the yeelding of ſuch maintenance and almes there muſt be ſo much ſpirituall, and conſequently voluntary as made them acceptable unto <hi>God;</hi> ſo will <hi>God</hi> himſelfe have the puniſhing of the non-performance, becauſe man cannot poſſibly be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Judge thereof: and hypocriſie in like manner being not diſcernable by man, and the puniſhment of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> miraculous; none can poſſibly, much leſſe may juſtly claime to doe the ſame, unleſſe they have the ſame power of miracles and diſcerning.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Peters</hi> profeſſing that what <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> did poſſeſſe was their owne, as afore; and our Saviour in the Parable, <hi>Math.</hi> 20.15. makes it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for us to doe what we will with our owne; I query by what Law wee can be compelled to part from that we have without our owne conſents? If <hi>Tythes,</hi> or whatſoever like them, be either <hi>Gods</hi> or <hi>Caeſars,</hi> I know a warrant for them: but as <hi>Caeſars Image</hi> entitled him to the tribute money, <hi>Math.</hi> 22.19. ſo doth <hi>God</hi> chiefly aime at the <hi>tribute of our conſciences,</hi> on which he ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped his owne image and likeneſſe in our father <hi>Adam</hi> at his creation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. But if the Tythes be the Miniſters, why doe we ſtill commit ſacriledge, withholding them in ſo many places of the Kingdome? Doe we not feare what befell <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> if our ſin be the ſame with theirs, as is by all tyth-maſters pretended? But if there bee nothing due to them by that Law, why doe we give them the gleanings under ſuch a Jewiſh notion? If we bee juſtified in one, we condemne our ſelves by the other.</p>
            <p>And whereas it is alledged, that if they which attend upon the miniſtery muſt be bound to live on ſuch almes onely as ſhall be voluntarily given them; it may likely prove a great temptation to frame their doctrine according to the peoples cares, for the farther inlargement of their maintenance. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that we have found it by experience a farre greater temptation with many men who being ſure of ſuch fat Benefices and yearly Incomes, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for their lives, tooke little care of often preaching, and how leane ſoules the people had; but when Churches ſhall be gathered and conſtituted accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our Saviours commiſſion, and the Apoſtles practice; we need not by Gods bleſſing to doubt of a powerfull Miniſtery, nor they of liberall mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; or in default thereof, that the denouncing of Gods threats and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121122:4"/>which are his owne ordinances, ſhould not ſufficiently prevaile upon the conſciences of men, if we had but faith therein, and forbore the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting of their perſons, which is the unwarrantable device of man: And as it would not have beene juſtifiable in the Apoſtles, if it lay in their power to prevent it, to be taken off from the Miniſtry to ſerve Tables, to ſpend time in ſeeing the poore provided for, <hi>Act.</hi> 6. beginning; ſo now may not Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans put the Miniſters of the Goſpel to get their living by working with their hands, it would be as great a ſinne and ſacriledge in us now, as withholding Tithes was under the Law; they ought to be liberally provided for, that they may live comfortably on the <hi>miniſtery of the Goſpel,</hi> as on <hi>their Altar,</hi> that they may, being void of all diſtractions, more freely imploy all thoughts and ſtudies on their miniſtery; but what ever extremity good Miniſters ſhould be reduced unto, through the hardneſſe of the people, or Gods intention to try their patience in this reſpect; it were farre more Apoſtolicall and Chriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like for Miniſters to labour as <hi>Paul</hi> did with his owne hands, than to force or require a ſubſiſtence in ſuch a manner, as being never appointed nor ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Lord Jeſus, makes the Goſpel ſeeme weariſome and chargeable.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Saviour,</hi> we know, told his Apoſtles that <hi>the workman was worthy of his hire,</hi> bidding them <hi>remaine eating and drinking in whatſoever houſe they came:</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> knew his right thereto ſo well, that he exhorts all Chriſtians to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate unto ſuch as taught them ſpirituall things, informing them that the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> prohibited the very muſling of an Oxe that trod out the corn, and inferres what greater care God takes of thoſe that labour in his vineyard, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.9, 10. Nay, though he tells us that other Apoſtles enjoyed this bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and that he was inferiour to none of them; yet it was better for him to dye, than ſo live as to make the Goſpel be thought chargeable. My brethren, what thinke we was the meaning of <hi>Pauls</hi> proceeding thus? No Miniſter can at preſent have better title unto Tythes or ſuch like maintenance, than <hi>Paul</hi> had in thoſe Primitive times, and yet he waved both all ſuch title and pretending, ſo often as his Diſciples were unwilling to be at charge thereof.</p>
            <p>Under the Law <hi>God required expreſly the tenth</hi> of all the people had, <hi>Lev.</hi> 27.32. and how ſuch were puniſhed that denyed or ſought evaſions, let theſe Tyth-maſters produce, and juſtifie it to bee their owne cauſe by their activity in doing of the like? But in the Goſpel wee finde nothing but <hi>The workman is worthy of his meat; The labourer is worthy of his hire; The Ox that trod the corne was not to be muſled; No man plants a Vineyard, or goeth to warfare at his owne charges; They which miniſter about holy things, live on the things of the Temple;</hi> and they which <hi>wait at the Altar are partakers of the Altar:</hi> This and the like is all we finde to this purpoſe throughout the Goſpel; and what can bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121122:5"/>from thence, but that in equitie the Goſpels Miniſters ſhould bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for? The Tithes are onely due unto the Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> (and that to o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>raine purpoſes, moſt whereof are void, aboliſh'd) which had no other inheritance, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.1. 'Tis they onely that can plead for them even in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of the Law, if it were now of force: But if that Tribe be dead, diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, not to be found, or appeare not to receive them; ſuch as have poſſeſſion both may and ought to keepe them, as being they onely who muſt give a ſtrict account thereof hereafter: And what account this is, would eaſily bee learned, if we did but take <hi>Paul</hi> and the other Apoſtles for our ſtudie and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. They tell us we muſt <hi>communicate unto him that teacheth in all good things, Gal.</hi> 6.6. and accordingly we finde that <hi>the beleevers had all things in common, Act.</hi> 4.32. So that if any thing of this nature may be inferr'd as a ſtanding law, from our Saviours commands, together with the Apoſtles and other Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans practice, it muſt be <hi>community of all things.</hi> And as it may doubtleſſe bee a great perfection in ſome particular Chriſtians to bee ſo liberall in diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their whole eſtates, even whilſt they are living, unto the neceſſity of the Saints; ſo farre better were it for the Civill State in generall, that there were a <hi>community of all things,</hi> than that a pretended Tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> (which though they had a rightfull title, are not the five hundreth part of the whole people) ſhould ſurfet on the tenth of all Gods creatures, and their increaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> tells the Philippians that they onely in the beginning of the Goſpel communicated unto his neceſſities, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.15, 16, 17. letting them withall underſtand, it was but their duty ſo to doe; and yet <hi>(marke)</hi> hee termes not what they gave him a reward of his deſerts, but as a gift from them; neither required he it at any time ſo much for his owne advantage and neceſſity, <hi>as a fruit of Gods grace in them;</hi> as an <hi>odour that ſmelleth ſweet;</hi> as <hi>a ſacrifice accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and well pleaſing unto God,</hi> from whence ſuch power proceeded, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. And as he tells the Corinthians upon the ſame occaſion, <hi>I write not theſe things to ſhame you, but as my beloved ſons to warne you,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4 12, 14.</p>
            <p>Oh the bleſſed ſpirit of <hi>Paul</hi> that knew thus to beguile men of their ſoules, by a ſanctified craftineſſe, and win them unto God by wiles l 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.16. Some few now adayes who are aſhamed to ſtand upon theſe Tythes, to ſue for them out of covetouſneſſe, or their private ends, as if they valued them for themſelves, but ſay they doe it to uphold the right thereof, and that they may not prejudice the title of their ſucceſſours; but conſider, deare Chriſtians, and you will finde even from the perſons and manners of ſuch proceedings, that all theſe are meere excuſes to colour their owne corruption (a crime no whit inferiour to that of <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira's</hi>) moſt raſhly cenſuring their ſucceſſours with the idolatry of covetouſneſſe (as if they knew who ſhould
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121122:5"/>ſucceed them after death) and ought not to judge otherwiſe than charitably of them beforehand, what e're they prove afterwards: but yet there is a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of <hi>Pauls</hi> to teach ſuch better, even againſt this palpable evaſion of theirs; <hi>Paul</hi> who it ſeemes was ſo farre from thinking it fitting to ſet out to ſale the miniſterie of the Goſpel, that even by his owne commandment and law (as I may ſay) was contented not to eate, unleſſe he did his dayes worke with his owne hands, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.10. did in conformity hereunto not onely forbeare to require wages of his Miniſterie from the <hi>Corinthians</hi> for himſelfe, but as is inſinuated, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.18. deſired <hi>Titus</hi> to doe the like, and ſo queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe would have required of others, if he had ſeene cauſe, or imagined that men would have been extravagantly covetous; which is an undeniable argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that <hi>Paſtours, Miniſters,</hi> and all other <hi>Church Officers,</hi> ought not to force maintenance, rewards or gifts from ſuch as will not pay them willingly.</p>
            <p>I know we are taught and bid diſtinguiſh times and ſeaſons, as though ſuch fond diſtinctions could as eaſily reconcile <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> as it doth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh all Sects and Hereſies with flouriſhes and ſhelterings for their moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident reſpective inventions of will-worſhip: But conſider, I beſeech you, you that cry out ſo much for diſtinguiſhing of times, will you make no diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction betweene <hi>types</hi> and <hi>autitypes?</hi> Is not <hi>God</hi> a <hi>Spirit,</hi> and will he not bee ſerved in <hi>ſpirit?</hi> even under the <hi>Law</hi> when <hi>God</hi> ſtood ſo ſtrictly upon his <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> yet <hi>David</hi> the man after Gods owne heart tells us, that praiſing and magnifying of his <hi>name,</hi> with other ſpirituall worſhip, was then more acceptable than ſacrifice, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.30, 31. But now under the Goſpel there is no ſacrifice, no worſhip, no ſervice beſide ſpirituall; what ever hee requires of us, or what ever wee performe unto him, 'tis onely the ſpirituall part thereof which he regards, which is accepted of him: Now as he lookes onely at the ſpirituall part, and as ſpirituall meanes can onely prevaile in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and diſpoſing people to ſpirituall ſervice; ſo it were prepoſterous to thinke that God ſhould approve or allow of any courſe which were not ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, much leſſe not capable to conduce unto ſuch ſpirituall ends and ſervice: amongſt the reſt, the communicating of our earthly ſubſtance unto the poore, and ſuch as ſtand in want, eſpecially to thoſe of <hi>the houſh Id of faith, Gal</hi> 6.10. unto the Saints, particularly for maintenance (as was ſaid before) of ſuch as <hi>miniſter to us in the Lord;</hi> even this I ſay, as all other duties of a Chriſtian muſt be ſpirituall; but how compelling men by compulſive courſes to pay tithes or ſuch like duties, can be a ſpiritual way of making men to pay them willingly, as if there were no compelling; or how the paying them unwillingly through threatning, or impriſonment, or other civill puniſhment, can poſſibly become a ſpirituall duty, and ſweet ſmelling ſacrifice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cceptable and well-pleaſing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, as <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, ſuch contribu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions ought to be; me thinkes any one that were not tempted as a ſharer of ſuch unrighteous Mainmon, if they did
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121122:6"/>but never ſo little conſider in the feare of God, would eaſily perceive and bee convinced.</p>
            <p>Which, that it may better prevaile upon them with Gods bleſſing, amongſt ſundry other evidences of <hi>Scripture,</hi> I will crave leave to reduce unto their memories this one of <hi>Pauls,</hi> who exhorting the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to ſuch like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions, diſtinguiſhes, and ſets thoſe that were not done grudingly, but as matter of bountie, in oppoſition to thoſe of covetouſneſſe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.5. And whether ſuch as are drawn from us by compulſion againſt our will, can prove matter of bountie; how we may warrantably bee conſtrain'd to ſacrifice the effects of covetouſneſſe unto God; or how ſuch involuntary and abortive fruits can poſſibly aſcend up as a ſweet ſavor into His noſtrils; I leave together with this Scripture and the reſt, to their more ſad and ſerious conſciences to ponder on.</p>
            <p>Since then the compelling men to pay tithes cannot cauſe that ſuch as are compelled, by ſo paying againſt their wils, to doe a ſpirituall duty or accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſervice unto God: perhaps ſome may ſay, Why may not men be forced to theſe as well as any other contributions or taxations which are rated and levied by order of the Civill Magiſtrate? I anſwer; that theſe other contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions are expreſly warranted by the Word of God, as Subſidies of Cuſtoms, Tolls, or any other taxes, whether for defence or honour of the Eſtate, or maintenance of the Civill Miniſters in ſervice of the Eſtates, wherein each in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitant participates and has a benefit. Secondly, ſuch ceſſements as are meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly civill. Thirdly, theſe tithes and maintenance may be required for ſuch a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall miniſtery, which perhaps ſome may, 1. not approve thereof: 2. they may likely thereupon ſcruple at it: 3. God will not have the miniſtery of the Goſpel to ſeeme chargeable to any: 4. hee never ordered any compulſive meanes to be uſed againſt thoſe that denyed ſuch Goſpel maintenance and contributions: 5. ſuch as neither approve nor participate of ſuch miniſtery, may likewiſe bee exempted in the contribution of charge thereof without any dammage or injury to others; in that the Miniſters, for number, may bee regulated according to the Miniſterie; and the Labourers encreaſed onely according to the harveſt; and laſtly, it were neither equitie nor juſtice to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell this or that man to contribute maintenance for the ſervice and miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of others, with whom he either cannot, or deſires not to joyne himſelfe: Holy <hi>David</hi> was ſo farre from ſuch a practice, that when <hi>Ornan</hi> the <hi>Iebuſite</hi> profered to give him his Threſhing ſloore to build an Altar, Oxen for burnt offerings, threſhing inſtruments for wood, wheat for meat offering, and all for nothing; <hi>David</hi> would needs pay for them at the full value; ſaying; <hi>I will not take that which is thine for the Lord, nor offer burnt offerings without coſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.22.23.24.</p>
            <p>But if any thing be now due in the nature of Tithes, and men bee juſtly
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121122:6"/>forced to make payment thereof; it muſt be Tithes preciſely; the tenth of all what ever we poſſeſſe; for we find not ſo much as a ſhadow in Scripture for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other warrant: &amp; according to this proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either the tenth man ſhould be a Miniſter of the Goſpel, or elſe the Miniſters being never ſo few, &amp; the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer the better cheer, ſharing among themſelves the tenth part of the revenues of all the Kingdom or Chriſtian world, each of them would have a yearly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come larger than that of Canterbuties: ſurely this is ſuch a temptation, that if ſuch as expect the ſweetneſſe of it may be judge thereof, as doubtleſſe they will never more away with Biſhops; ſo they will as certainly bee deſirous, and no wayes be prevailed upon, till God turne their hearts, not to enjoy ſuch large eſtates, which through pretence of enabling them to become hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and attend upon their miniſterie, will as infallibly make them degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate into drones and dumb Teachers as ever were Biſhops of any Country.</p>
            <p>But if perhaps they ſhould be ſo modeſt for the preſent as to ſay they bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aime at maintenance; 200. or 300. pounds <hi>per annum</hi> ſhall bee the height of their ambition, &amp;c. I anſwer, 1. that what e're the maintenance be, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more or leſſe, our chiefe care ought to ſee it ſetled in ſuch a way as were warrantable from the Apoſtles practice here on earth, and ſanctified by God above: If we want this ground-worke, the foundation which wee build on being ſandy, no marvell if we attend a bleſſing thereof in vaine. 2. I anſwer, that for ſuch as are not ſpiritually minded, 200. or 300. pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> and a farre leſſe revenue certaine, is as great a temptation to thoſe whoſe anceſtors perhaps were never worth the tithes thereof; I ſay it is as great a templation and altogether as ſufficient to make ſuch intrude into the Miniſterie for love of the maintenance, as a more corpulent fat Biſhopricke: it is the lazie but conſtant Benefice which for the moſt part doth firſt corrupt their younger thoughts and actions: from whence according to the ſame depraved prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples they afterwards aſpire unto a Biſhopricke, which perhaps their more inferiour aimes did never thinke upon before. But it ſhould bee the love of God and not of Mammon which winnes men to the Miniſtery of the Goſpel. Deare Chriſtians, let it not be offenſive to you, nor give occaſion to thinke I want charitie towards the Miniſters of Chriſt, that ſhare unto us of their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall things, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.11. (I dare call <hi>God</hi> to be my witneſſe to the contrary) if I aske how few there are who take <hi>Orders</hi> and apply themſelves unto the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie out of pure zeale unto the <hi>Goſpel?</hi> and how many on the other ſide, chiefly out of a deſigne to live upon it, as if it were the eaſieſt way to grow rich and get a living by; making the <hi>Miniſtery<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d mercenary trade,</hi> and as much as in them lyes endeavouring to <hi>bity and ſell the gifts of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> for which <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was deemed by <hi>Peter</hi> to be in the <hi>gall of bitterneſſe, in the bond of iniquity,</hi> and doomed to periſh together with his money, unleſſe he did repent thereof? <hi>Act.</hi> 8.20, 22, 23.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:121122:7"/>
            <p>Good Reader, reſolve this queſtion in thine owne heart before thou paſſe on farther: doth not thine owne experience informe thy conſcience, that even too great a part of <hi>Miniſters,</hi> however <hi>God</hi> may ſince upon their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance have had mercy on them, have heretofore, by what appeares, been too too much prevailed upon in this reſpect? nay doe not ſuch ſcroules and Catalogues of ſcandalous Miniſters even at this day fully demonſtrate ſo much? and can a <hi>Synod,</hi> a <hi>Parliament,</hi> a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> after ſo great light of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> permit the ſame temptations unqueſtioned, wherein our predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours ſo ſhamefully miſcaried? <hi>Forbid it good God in anger, if not in love, and that with ſpeed; leſt this enormous ſinne having helped to fill up the meaſure of our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, thy juſt wrath and indignation burſt out upon us as hot as fire, untill it quite conſume the diſconſolate remnant of this unhappy Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is it to partake in other mens ſinnes by laying hands ſuddenly on ſuch as take upon them the miniſterie of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> forbid? 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. if it be not what was practiſed heretofore in <hi>England:</hi> I wiſh I could heare of ſome meanes taken for preventing it hereafter.</p>
            <p>A young Scholar (and how reproveable young Scholars are is well known to thoſe that live neare them) having already, or intending to make love un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a fat Paſſonage, or ſome pretty parcell of Tithes, applyes himſelfe unto One or more; a Biſhop or Presbytery of which he was ſeldome or never ſeene be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in all his life time, deſiring to be admitted into the Miniſtery of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel upon payment of certaine fees: perhaps they uſed heretofore, and may againe hereafter examine ſuch a one upon ſome few queſtions, and give him a Text to try whether his Common-place bookes, with ſuch like ready helps can furniſh him with a Sermon. Alas my Brethren, neither your queſtions, though they were multiplyed, with his anſwers, nor yet a Sermon or two are competent tryalls of his gifts; they muſt be ſuch as have knowne his conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation; ſuch as have eate and drunke with him; and beene witneſſes to the integrity of his life, and ſeene his ſtudies, with the fruits thereof, that are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly able to judge of his abilities, whether he be capable of ſo high a calling. How wofull then muſt it needs be when none may <hi>call</hi> him, ſave they who for the moſt part, if it may be ſaid a <hi>calling, call,</hi> or rather lay hands on, they know not who?</p>
            <p>I dread to thinke how uſuall it is with many to ruſh themſelves moſt Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniacally and ſacrilegiouſly into the Miniſtery, and yet with greater won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring and amazement that this arch-temptation and grand ſtumbling-blocke of Tythes, which ſo many of our bleſſed Martyrs have even to death ſo much inveighed againſt, ſhould yet remaine the greateſt Idoll and hindrance of <hi>Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as Tythes or other maintenance to the Miniſters are no Civill Legall debt; ſo neither are almes to the poore, but both alike are to be made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121122:7"/>by a voluntary communicating to them of what we have, according as their reſpective neceſſities ſhall require: wee are bound in equity to both, and ſin damnably if we come ſhort with either: but no warrant or Law of God doth authorize any man to compell ſuch as will not willingly comply therein; the producing ſuch order out of Gods word to be now of force un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, lyes on them which muſt in ſuch caſe be plaintiſes, and make claime thereto: no man being bound to part from any thing which is his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per goods, and afterwards be put to ſue for it againe: Preſcription beares ſway no longer when the paying or parting from any thing is diſcovered to contract a guiltineſſe of conſcience.</p>
            <p>But for ſuch whom it concernes not in point of conſcience, it is yet better to acknowledge and make payment of ſuch Tithes, than confeſſing ſome ſuch debt or dutie to bee due, leave it to the determination of thoſe who are to have the benefit thereof what proportion of their eſtates they will require; it is farre better to bee at a certainty of a harder meaſure, than truſt unto their mercy.</p>
            <p>Call to minde the two ſhillings and nine pence, remember with what ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemency and diligence it was proſecuted: God was pleaſed to blaſt it not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding: But had it once beene ſetled, and mens purſes with their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences brought under contribution of their prerogative, as they might as legally have doubled or trebled it upon any occaſion afterwards, and that not without pretending full arrerages: So wee may bee certaine, this onely priviledge of theirs would have quite devoured the ſubjects whole propriety: and this conſequence have thereupon ſucceeded: that afterwards there would have beene little need to trouble Parliaments with graunting Subſidies, the Clergie, for continuance of their greatneſſe, might likely have beene no leſſe willing, than it would have beene able to ſupply ſuch trifling ſummes out of their boundleſſe Revenues.</p>
            <p>I know it will be objected, that ſuch and ſuch great Clerkes and Doctors are all with greateſt might and maine for Tithes.</p>
            <p>To every one in particular, and againſt them all in generall (ſave one to whom I crave leave to ſpeake a word a part, beſeeching God it may prove ſeaſonable) with whole Cathedralls full, how many ſoever there bee of them: I will oppoſe onely the bleſſed Scriptures, and ſuch deſpiſed Chriſtians as moſt exactly bare witneſſe to them; as they whoſe fooliſhneſſe will yet in time appeare of deepeſt wiſedome, their poverty of greateſt value, and their weakneſſe of ſuch invincible ſtrength, that they, and onely they will at laſt infallibly overcome and judge the world, with all their vaine imaginations.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:121122:8"/>
            <p>The Diſcourſe entitled <hi>A new diſcovery of perſonall Tithes,</hi> or, <hi>The tenth part of mens cleere gaines,</hi> pretends <q>the tenth part of whatſoever any perſon of any profeſſion doth any wayes lawfully advance, to be due unto the Miniſter of the Goſpel both by the Law of God and man, unleſſe ſome ſpeciall cuſtome, compoſition, or priviledge of the place allowed by Law exempt him, pag. 1</q> Now wee know that amongſt ſeverall others, the publike practice and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Uſurers is neither of the rareſt nor leaſt gainſome in Chriſtendome, (to the ſhame of all ſuch be it ſpoken) no one trade produces ſuch certaine nor ſo much gaine throughout the world: But by what Law of <hi>God</hi> the <hi>tenth</hi> hereof, and of a thouſand other <hi>unwarrantable,</hi> I may ſay <hi>damnable</hi> increaſings, becomes due unto the Clergie, I know not, unleſſe by their conniving, in not reproving us in theſe ſinfull courſes, out of a deſigne to wreſt that Scripture to prove it, where we are required to <hi>make us friends of our unrighteous mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Luke</hi> 16.9.</p>
            <p>But if any one ſhall ſay that Uſurie or ſuch unlawfull gaines were not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. I anſwer, that ſince none are exempted but by ſpeciall priviledge, the words inferre <hi>all gaines</hi> to bee <hi>lawfull</hi> which the Lawes of the Land per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or could not puniſh, innumerable particulars whereof the Law of God abominates: and though many profeſſions of themſelves bee lawfull, yet the greateſt part of all their gaines is otherwiſe moſt commonly. But can we juſtly blame theſe men that are ſo good accountants? that have ſuch care of themſelves and families? They require not onely the tenth part of all the foure Elements produce, as Corne, Fruit, Fiſh and Fowle of all ſorts; the tenth part of all increaſe in Cattell, and of Poultry; the tenth of all houſe-rent; but alſo the tenth part of what is gained by Handicraft, Manufactures and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize, or any kinde of bargaining, &amp;c. which yet is more than double as much as all the reſt in value: ſurely we may well anſwer theſe men with Ye know not what ye aske, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.22. as our Saviour did thoſe two Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, not more ambitious than theſe are avaritious. And yet the Authour of the ſaid Diſcourſe profeſſed that he thought himſelf bound in conſcience to make diſcovery how due theſe <hi>Perſonall tithes</hi> are, chiefly <hi>to pull ſundry honeſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians out of a damnable ſinne;</hi> leſt through his ſilence he ſhould bee both guilty thereof and of their blood, <hi>pag.</hi> 3. But ſince on the contrary (as I hope) hee is by this time fully informed how many mens ſin and blood he may have been deeply acceſſory to, though himſelfe never thought thereof, in publiſhing ſo unjuſtifiable, ſo unhappy a Diſcovery: Oh how acceptable would it bee to all rightly informed conſcientious Chriſtans, ſince the Father of mercies hath given ſo large a time to ſee ſo great a miſtake retracted? Such publike offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces require no leſſe than publike acknowledgement and remorce, if perhaps the gui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tineſſe may be forgiven, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.22.</p>
            <p>This Idoll, this golden wedge of Tithes was execrated in moſt, if not in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121122:8"/>all other Countries by the firſt Reformers, onely Epiſcopacy has thus repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the worſhipping of it ſo long in England; and unleſſe theſe gods of theirs be ſent away packing with them, as it is impoſſible that either of them can chaſtly long obſerve a voluntary withdrawing from each other, much leſſe an unwilling parting; ſo may we be as certaine, that <hi>where ever ſuch a carkeis is, there will be the Eagles</hi> (of ſpirituall prey) <hi>gathered together, Math.</hi> 24.28. if not the worſt of ravenous carrion Crowes.</p>
            <p>And in regard this is a ſubject, which through the ſucceſſive iniquitie of the times has not beene permitted to be treated on; as it cannot bee expected but much will be omitted which might be produced againſt it: ſo if any thing which is ſuperfluous, or that might have beene ſpared is yet alledged; the wel affected Reader as he is bound in charity, ſo is he requeſted in all courteſie to ſeeke to ſalve it by Chriſtian admoniſhing and reproofe. It cannot upon due triall be found unſeaſonable at ſuch a time when Civill and Church eſtate are both to be reformed, to have ſaid ſomewhat about this Cankerworme, which with ſuch peſtilent influence reflects and feeds upon them both. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law two witneſſes were as good as twentie even in caſe of Civill death; and if but two be found to witneſſe againſt this monſter, ſuch as are wanting may be the better ſpared; but through Gods gracious aſſiſtance we are ſufficiently provided, if the Goſpel of truth it ſelfe wherein wee have a compleat Jury of Apoſtles, and our bleſſed Saviour not diſdaining to be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, may be beleeved, and prevaile with us in a cauſe which ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes our ſelves, the intereſt of all Eſtates.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Saviour</hi> in his Commiſſion to the Apoſtles for preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, inſerts this injunction, viz. <hi>Freely ye have received, freely give, Math.</hi> 20. <hi>from verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>to</hi> 8. Into whatſoever City ye enter, and they receive you, <hi>eate ſuch things as are ſet before you, Luke</hi> 10.8. In obedience whereunto <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes unto the <hi>Theſſalonians, Ye may remember our labouring night and day, becauſe wee would not be chargeable unto any of you,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.9. and in that reſpect tels the <hi>Corinthians, It were better for him to dye than that any man ſhould make his glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing void,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9, 15. My <hi>Brethren,</hi> have we not here the expreſſe commands of God concerning his <hi>Miniſters maintenance,</hi> and <hi>Pauls</hi> conforming there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, both related to us by inſpiration of the <hi>bleſſed Spirit?</hi> and will wee yet from a <hi>typicall</hi> prohibition onely of not muſling an Oxe that trod out the corne under the Law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.4. preſume to leavie maintaintenance by force of armes for the Miniſterie of the Goſpel? when it appeares plainly by <hi>Paul</hi> in the beginning of that Chapter where he quotes the ſame words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.9. that we are now onely bound by the equity thereof: that is, Chriſtians are now obliged in conſcience to order matters in ſuch manner that Miniſters of the Goſpell might live comfortably of the <hi>Goſpel, verſ.</hi> 14. and <hi>Paul</hi> had this power as well as other Apoſtles, <hi>v.</hi> 3 4. to require it by exhortation; and yet
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121122:9"/>he never uſed it towards the <hi>Corinthians, leſt he ſhould hinder the Goſpel of Chriſt, v.</hi> 12. But what power is it which <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes he never exerciſed towards the <hi>Corinthians?</hi> not a <hi>Civill</hi> power; for we doe not finde in any place that ever he had ſuch a power; but a power he had to <hi>eate and drinke ſuch things as were ſet before him,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.4. with <hi>Luke</hi> 10.8. And as the beleevers were bound in conſcience to give them a competent allowance to live upon, ſo the Apoſtles both might and ought to preſſe it upon their conſciences, receiving it as a gift, not to ſatisfie their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe, nor yet ſo much for ſupplying their owne neceſſities, as out of a deſire <hi>that the fruit thereof might abound to the Donors accounts, Phil.</hi> 4.17. I know the exceptions will be, that if Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters muſt have no other maintenance but what good Chriſtians will give them of their own accords; the Univerſities will become ſolitary, Learning of no account, and the Miniſtery of the Goſpel grow contemptible and quite deſerted. To this ſeeming threefold cord of objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I will onely anſwer, that theſe are all but <hi>feares</hi> and <hi>jealouſies</hi> of mortall men at belt, which may not be put in competition, much leſſe make void our <hi>Saviours Commiſſion</hi> and <hi>Pauls practice,</hi> both which proceeded from the infallible Spirit of God for preaching of the Goſpel <hi>freely;</hi> which whileſt it was practiſed in the Primitive times proved ſo ſucceſſefull, and amongſt other bleſſed effects wrought ſo powerfully upon their ſpirits, as that we finde not a few onely, but even <hi>all that beleeved had all things common, who ſelling their goods and poſſeſſions parted them to all men as they had need, Act.</hi> 2.44.45. Doe we thinke the Apoſtles or other Miniſters could want amongſt Chriſtians that were thus all of one minde, <hi>no man ſaying that any thing was his owne which he poſſeſſed, Act</hi> 4.32? Or doe we diſtruſt Gods providence, and thinke his <hi>Ordinances</hi> have not the ſame bleſſings both ſpirituall and temporall accompanying them, if wee be alike faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in ſubmitting unto them? or if a Miniſter which truly laboureth in the <hi>Goſpel</hi> ſhall really want maintenance, may hee betake himſelfe to requiring it by <hi>compulſive</hi> meanes, or elſe not preach at all, or preach unwillingly, for which he has no preſident in <hi>Scripture,</hi> neglecting <hi>Pauls</hi> example, <hi>who wrought with his owne hands, that he might make the Goſpel without charge,</hi> and yet thinke to ſhare reward with <hi>Paul</hi> in heaven? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.17.18. hee may ſteale as well (for 'tis a <hi>robbing</hi> them of that <hi>Goſpel</hi> which was directed to them, if he withhold it totally, ſet ſuch a price on it, or in ſuch a manner as God never gave commiſſion) and though he eſcape on earth, <hi>his ſinnes will follow after him to judgement,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.24. He that walketh in darkneſſe knoweth not whither he goeth, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 12.35. he may be in hell before he be aware. <hi>Since then light is come into the world, let us not</hi> be found to <hi>love darkneſſe rather than light, Iohn</hi> 3.19. the Epidemicall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption throughout all Chriſtendome, of mens thruſting themſelves into the Miniſtery meerly to make a <hi>gaine</hi> thereof, which <hi>Paul</hi> diſavowed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.17. and not ſincerely for the Goſpels ſake: For as it cannot be denied but ſuch are more ſwayed with the love of lucre than of Chriſt, ſo is it an undoubted cauſe that their endeavours ever ſince have proved ſo unprofitable unto the people, ſtill remaining for the moſt part without any power of godlineſſe, ſecure in ignorance, dead in ſin: whereas we obſerved before the great ſucceſſefulnes wherewith God was pleaſed to bleſſe the contrary practice in the Apoſtles times; and if yet we ſhall apply our ſelves to follow them in this particular, God can no more be wanting to ſecond us with a bleſſing, than to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny himſelfe in ſuffering his owne <hi>Ordinances</hi> to be ineffectuall, injurious to his people, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiciall to his Goſpels cauſe. On let us try our good God herein before wee cenſure Him of unfaithfulneſſe: and the <hi>Lord</hi> in much mercy prevent, that this temptation remaine no more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, to the great ſcandall of our B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>thren of Scotland, and other Proteſtant Churches; not without great ſhame unto our ſelves in this world, and imminent danger of raſing up againſt us in the world to come.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
